Chapter 55. Of the monstrous pictures of whales.
I shall air long paint to you as well as one can without canvas something like
the true form of the whale as he actually appears to the eye of the
whaleman when in his own absolute body the whale is mored alongside the whale
ship so that he can be fairly stepped upon there. It may be worthwhile,
therefore, previously to advert to those curious imaginary portraits of him,
which even down to the present day, confidently challenged the faith of the
landsmen. It is time to set the world right in this matter by proving such
pictures of the whale all wrong.
It may be that the primal source of all those pictorial delusions will be found
among the oldest Hindu, Egyptian and Grecian sculptures forever since those
inventive but unscrupulous times when on the marble panelings of temples, the
pedestals of statues and on shields, medallions, cups and coins, the dolphin
was drawn in scales of chain armor like saladines and a helmeted head like St.
George's. Ever since then has something of the same sort of license prevailed
not only in most popular pictures of the whale but in many scientific
presentations of him. Now by all odds the most ancient extant portrait anyways
purporting to be the whales is to be found in the famous cavern pagod of
elephant in India. The brahinss maintain that in the almost endless sculptures of
that immemorial pagod all the trades and pursuits every conceivable avocation of
man were prefigured ages before any of them actually came into being. No wonder
then that in some sort our noble profession of whailing should have been
there shadowed forth. The Hindu whale referred to occurs in a separate
department of the wall depicting the incarnation of Vishnu in the form of
Leviathan, learnedly known as the Mati Avatar. But though this sculpture is
half man and half whale, so as only to give the tail of the latter, yet that
small section of him is all wrong. It looks more like the tapering tail of an
anaconda than the broad palms of the true whale's majestic flukes.
But go to the old galleries and look now at a great Christian painters's portrait
of this fish, for he succeeds no better than the antidoluvian Hindu. It is
Guido's picture of Perseus rescuing Andromeda from the sea monster or whale.
Where did Guido get the model of such a strange creature as that? Nor does
Hogarth in painting the same scene in his own hers descending make out one wit
better. The huge corpulence of that Hogarthian monster undulates on the
surface scarcely drawing one inch of water. It has a sort of howa on its back
and its distended tusked mouth into which the billows are rolling might be
taken for the traitor's gate leading from the tempames by water into the
tower. Then there are the padrois whales of old scotch sibald and Jonah's whale
as depicted in the prints of old bibles in the cuts of old primmers. What shall
be said of these? As for the bookbinders whale, winding like a vinetock round the
stock of a descending anchor, as stamped and gilded on the backs and title pages
of many books, both old and new, that is a very picturesque but purely fabulous
creature imitated, I take it, from like figures on antique vases.
Though universally denominated a dolphin, I nevertheless call this
Bookbinder's fish an attempt at a whale because it was so intended when the
device was first introduced. It was introduced by an old Italian publisher
somewhere about the 15th century during the revival of learning and in those
days and even down to a comparatively late period, dolphins were popularly
supposed to be a species of the Leviathan.
In the vignettes and other embellishments of some ancient books,
you will at times meet with very curious touches at the whale, where all manner
of spouts, jets, dauo, hot springs and cold, saratoga, and boden boden come
bubbling up from his unexhausted brain.
In the title page of the original edition of the advancement of learning,
you will find some curious whales.
But quitting all these unprofessional attempts, let us glance at those
pictures of Leviathan purporting to be sober scientific delineations by those
who know. In old Harris's collection of voyages, there are some plates of whales
extracted from a Dutch book of voyages AD 1671 entitled A Whailing Voyage to
Spitsburgen in the ship Jonas and the Whale Peter Peterson of Freezeland
Master. In one of those plates, the whales like great rafts of logs are
represented lying among ice isles with white bears running over their living
backs. In another play the prodigious blunder is made of representing the
whale with perpendicular flukes. Then again there is an imposing quarto
written by one captain Colnet a post captain in the English Navy entitled a
voyage round Capehorn into the South Seas for the purpose of extending the
spermicetti whale fisheries. In this book is an outline purporting to be a
quote picture of a visitor or spermiceti whale drawn by scale from one killed on
the coast of Mexico August 1793 and hoisted on deck. I doubt not the captain
had this voracious picture taken for the benefit of his marines. To mention but
one thing about it, let me say that it has an eye which applied according to
the accompanying scale to a fullgrown sperm whale would make the eye of that
whale a bow window some 5 ft long. Ah, my gallant captain, why did you not give
us Jonah looking out of that eye?
Nor are the most conscientious compilations of natural history for the
benefit of the young and tender free from the same heinousness of mistake.
Look at that popular work Goldsmith's animated nature. In the abridged London
edition of 1807, there are plates of an alleged whale and a narwhale. I do not
wish to seem inelegant, but this unsightly whale looks much like an
amputated SA. And as for the narwhale, one glimpse at it is enough to amaze one
that in this 19th century such a hippogri could be palmed for genuine
upon any intelligent public of school boys.
Then again in 1825, Bernard German, Count Deassiped, a great naturalist, published a
scientific systematized whale book, wherein are several pictures of the
different species of the Leviathan. All these are not only incorrect, but the
picture of the mysticetus or Greenland whale, that is to say the right whale,
even Scoresby, a long experienced man as touching that species, declares not to
have its counterpart in nature.
But placing of the cap sheath to all this blundering business was reserved
for the scientific Frederick Kuvier, brother to the famous Baron. In 1836,
he published a natural history of whales in which he gives what he calls a
picture of the sperm whale. Before showing that picture to any Nantucketer,
you would best provide for your summary retreat from Nantucket. In a word,
Frederick Kouier's sperm whale is not a sperm whale, but a squash. Of course, he
never had the benefit of a whaling voyage. Such men seldom have. But once
he derived that picture, who can tell?
Perhaps he got it as his scientific predecessor in the same field. Deare got
one of his authentic abortions, that is from a Chinese drawing. And what sort of
lively lads with the pencil those Chinese are, many queer cups and saucers
inform us. As for these signpainers whales seen in the streets hanging over
the shops of oil dealers, what shall be said of them? They are generally Richard
III whales with dramadary humps and very savage, breakfasting on three or four
sailor tarts, that is whaleboats full of mariners, their deformities floundering
in seas of blood and blue paint. But these manifold mistakes in depicting the
whale are not so very surprising after all. Consider most of these scientific
drawings have been taken from the stranded fish. And these are about as
correct as a drawing of a wrecked ship with broken back would correctly
represent the noble animal itself in all its undashed pride of hull and spars.
Though elephants have stood for their full lengths, the living Leviathan has
never yet fairly floated himself for his portrait. The living whale, in all his
full majesty and significance, is only to be seen at sea in unfathomable
waters, and afloat the vast bulk of him is out of sight, like a launched line of
battleship. And out of that element it is a thing eternally impossible for
mortal man to hoist him bodily into the air so as to preserve all his mighty
swells and undulations.
And not to speak of the highly presumable difference of contour between
a young sucking whale and a fullgrown Plutonian Leviathan. Yet even in the
case of one of those young sucking whales hoisted to a ship's deck, such as
then the outlandish eel-like limbered varying shape of him that his precise
expression the devil himself could not catch.
But it may be fancied that from the naked skeleton of the stranded whale
accurate hints may be derived touching his true form. Not at all. For it is one
of the more curious things about this Leviathan that his skeleton gives very
little idea of his general shape. Though Jeremy Bentham's skeleton, which hangs
for a candalabra in the library of one of his executives, correctly conveys the
idea of a burly brow utilitarian old gentleman, with all Jeremy's other
leading personal characteristics. Yet nothing of this kind could be inferred
from any Leviathan's articulated bones.
In fact, as the great hunter says, the mere skeleton of the whale bears the
same relation to the fully invested and padded animal as the insect does to the
chrysalis that so roundingly envelops it. This peculiarity is strikingly
evinced in the head, as in some parts of this book will incidentally be shown. It
is also very curiously displayed in the side fin, the bones of which almost
exactly answer to the bones of the human hand, minus only the thumb. This fin has
four regular bone fingers, the index, middle, ring, and little finger. But all
these are permanently lodged in their fleshy covering, as the human fingers in
an artificial covering. However recklessly the whale may sometimes serve
us, said humorous Stub one day, he can never be truly said to handle us without mittens.
For all these reasons, then any way you may look at it, you must needs conclude
that the great Leviathan is that one creature in the world which must remain
unpainted to the last. True, one portrait may hit the mark much nearer
than another, but none can hit it with any very considerable degree of
exactness. So there is no earthly way of finding out precisely what the whale
really looks like. And the only mode in which you can derive even a tolerable
idea of his living contour is by going a whailing yourself. But by so doing, you
run no small risk of being eternally stove and sunk by him. Wherefore, it
seems to me you had best not be too fidious in your curiosity touching this Leviathan.